A Finding Aid to the Jay DeFeo Papers, circa 1940s-1970s, in the Archives of American Art AAA.defejay
Archives of American Art
Jay DeFeo papers
circa 1940s-1970s
AAA.defejay
Archives of American Art
1.3 Linear feet
The papers of artist Jay DeFeo measure 1.3 linear feet and date from circa 1940s to circa 1970s. The collection documents her career through biographical material, correspondence with friends, personal business records, writings, printed material, artwork, and photographs.
DeFeo, Jay, 1929-1989
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 7 series
Series 1: Biographical material, 1948-1969 (1 folder; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1960-1970s (0.3 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1960s (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1964-1974 (2 folders; Box 1)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1950s-1970s (2 folders; Box 1, OV 3)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1940s-1970s (0.4 linear feet; Box 1, OV 3)
Series 7: Artwork, circa 1950s-1960s (0.2 linear feet; Box 2)
Scope and Contents note
The papers of artist Jay DeFeo measure 1.3 linear feet and date from circa 1940s to circa 1970s. The collection documents her career through biographical material, correspondence with friends, personal business records, writings, printed material, artwork, and photographs.
About half of the collection is made up of correspondence and photographs. DeFeo maintained ongoing communications with many artists, friends, and business associates. Notable correspondence is with Wallace and Shirley Berman, Irving Blum/Ferus Gallery, Bruce Conner, Frank Lobdell, Fred Martin, Michael McClure, Margaret Peterson, Deborah Remington, Ruth Terrill, and Eleanor (Nell) Sinton. The photographs document her adult years, although there are some as a teenager. DeFeo, her artist husband Wally Hedrick, and friends appear in many of the images. The remainder of the collection includes printed materials, exhibition information, some writings and some limited artwork. The collection is particularly rich in documentation on her artwork, The Rose.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated between 1975-1981 by Jay DeFeo.
Related Archival Materials note
The Archives of American Art has an oral history interview with DeFeo conducted 1975 June 3-1976 January 23 by Paul Karlstrom for the Archives of America Art. An 83 page transcript is available online.
The Bancroft Library at the University of California, Berkeley holds some of DeFeo's archival materials.
Biographical/Historical note
Jay DeFeo (1929-1989) lived and worked in Northern California where she was a prominent figure in the San Francisco Bay Area art scene as a painter in the progressive art community. She identified her artistic style as expressionist and symbolist.
DeFeo was born in Hanover, New Hampshire, and was three years old when her family moved to the Bay Area. She attended the University of California Berkeley and earned an Associate’s Degree in 1948, a B.A. in 1950 and a M.A. in Fine Arts in 1951. After earning the M.A. she took 18 months to travel in France, Spain, northern Africa, and Italy. She spent 6 months in Florence where she painted and produced her first important body of work. DeFeo returned to San Francisco at the end of her trip.
DeFeo married fellow artist Wally Hedrick in 1954. They settled in a large Victorian flat at 2322 Fillmore Street and actively participated in Beat counter culture. DeFeo and Hedrick counted many artists among their friends and colleagues, including musicians, painters, poets, and photographers. They threw large parties with hundreds of guests. DeFeo produced a range of works during her four-decade long career. She began working on her most celebrated and massive painting, The Rose, in the Fillmore flat.
In the mid-1960s, DeFeo began teaching at the San Francisco Art Institute. She and Wally Hedrick divorced in 1969, and she moved to Larkspur in Marin County to regroup from personal set-backs and the draining experience of working on The Rose. In 1980 she joined the art faculty at Mills College. She maintained personal and professional correspondences with many people, and her papers include letters about conservation efforts for The Rose.
Berman, Shirley; Berman, Wallace, 1926-1976; Blum, Irving, 1930-; Conner, Bruce; Hedrick, Wally, 1928-2003; Lobdell, Frank, 1921-; Martin, Fred; McClure, Michael; Peterson, Margaret, 1903-; Remington, Deborah; Sinton, Nell, 1910-1997; Terrill, Ruth; Painters--California--San Francisco Bay Area; Photographers--California--San Francisco Bay Area; Photographs; Photography--California--San Francisco; Photography--California--San Francisco Bay Area; Women artists; Works of art
- Biographical Material, 1948-1969; Series 1; 1 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  This series has limited materials about Jay DeFeo’s life. These include a passport, her Associates Degree from the University of California, Berkeley, and the start and end dates of her marriage to Wally Hedrick.
  - Biographical Documents, 1948-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1960-1970s; Series 2; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  This series makes up a significant portion of the collection. DeFeo maintained correspondence with a range of friends and colleagues. Letters and cards to and from friends include discussions of life in San Francisco, personal difficulties, references to DeFeo’s jewelry-making, or supportive comments about DeFeo’s artwork. Bruce Conner and DeFeo have an especially extensive set of letters about The Rose. Also included are several photo collage postcards from Wallace Berman, and a photo collage from Dean Stockwell to DeFeo. Letters from galleries or art institutions are also represented in the collection. Other correspondents include Fred Martin, Dorothy Miller, Frank Lobdell, Margaret Peterson, Irving Blum/Ferus Gallery, Michael McClure, Eleanor (Nell) Sinton, Wallace and Shirley Berman, Deborah Remington, and Ruth Terrill.
  - A, miscellaneous, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Berman, Wallace, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Conner, Bruce, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Demetrion, Jim, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ferus Gallery, 1964-1965; 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Green, Mark, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - G, miscellaneous, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hedrick, Wally, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hoobby, Wendi, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - H, miscellaneous, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - L, miscellaneous, 1967-1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Martin, Fred, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - M, miscellaneous, 1961-1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - N, miscellaneous, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Pasadena Art Museum, 1962-1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - P, miscellaneous, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - R, miscellaneous, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - San Francisco Museum of Art, 1968-1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - S, miscellaneous, 1967-1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Sinton, Nell, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Terrill, Ruth, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - U, miscellaneous, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Unidentified or First name Only, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - W, miscellaneous, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Y, miscellaneous, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Writings, circa 1960s; Series 3; 3 Folders Box 1
  This series contains lengthy reflections by Fred Martin on art and travel, sheet music from Wally Hedrick's Studio 13 Jazz Band, bits of draft text for a Frank Lobdell catalogue by Walter Hopps, and poems published in SEMINA.
  - Martin, Fred, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hedrick, Wally, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Personal Business Records, 1964-1974; Series 4; 2 Folders Box 1
  The personal and business records series contains various financial information, including receipts for art supplies, a checking account registry, and the lease for 2322 Fillmore Street. Purchase information for her painting Incision is available. A check that DeFeo wrote to the San Francisco Museum of Art Conservation Laboratory to cover initial costs for preservation of The Rose is present. Also found is contract information for teaching at the San Francisco Art Institute.
  - Financial, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - San Francisco Art Institute, San Francsico Museum of Art, 1964-1974 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Printed Material, circa 1950s-1970s; Series 5; 3 Folders Box 1, OV 3
  This series contains catalogs, announcements and posters from galleries and museums for exhibitions of work by Jay DeFeo, Wallace Berman, Wally Hedrick, Weyman Lew, Fred Martin, Michael McClure, and Arthur Richer. Also includes articles about The Rose conservation, and other writings from newspapers and periodicals.
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1960-1975 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Oversize Magazine Artforum, 1963 (Box OV 3)
  - Magazine Fragment of DeFeo with The Rose, 1961 (Box OV 3)
- Photographs, circa 1940s-1970s; Series 6; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1, OV 3
  Photographs include an extensive collection of friends, parties, and trips to the beach. DeFeo appears in a large number of the images. Joan Brown and Wally Hedrick are in many pictures, Manuel Neri in some. Linus Pauling is in one large photograph. Photos of the Fillmore Street flat are present, as well as many images of Christmas time. Some photographs were taken by Wallace Berman. Also included are some photographs on contact sheets and some which measure approximately 1 inch by 1 inch. Also included is one folder of negatives.
  - DeFeo, Jay, circa 1940s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Friends, Pets, Others, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Friends, Pets, Others, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Beaches and Other Trips, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - DeFeo Artwork, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Fillmore St. Flat and Parties, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Hedrick, Wally, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
    One oversized item housed in OV 3.
  - Works of Art (not DeFeo), undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Negatives, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Oversized Photograph of Wally Hedrick from Box 1, Folder 39 (Box OV 3)
- Artwork, circa 1950s-1960s; Series 7; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2
  This series contains many collages, some created by DeFeo. A slice of The Rose is included, with note from DeFeo that one year she sent pieces of the work as Christmas cards. Sketches by Al Wong are present.
  - Collage "Batman Gallery", circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Collage "Bunk Johnson", circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Collages, Piece of The Rose, Sketches, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 3)